- One of the misperceptions on the crypto side
is that Ether ETFs weren't as successful
as the Bitcoin ETFs.
We're really by all accounts in the ETF world.
The Ether ETFs had really successful launches.
So how do we measure that?
First and foremost, for us in the industry,
a successful ETF is one that delivers
what it's supposed to deliver.
- Welcome to Bankless, where we explore the frontier
of internet money and internet finance.
This is how to get started,
how to get better and how to front-run the opportunity.
I'm David Hoffman, just me today,
and I'm here to help you become more Bankless.
Extremely powerful episode today.
It's not every day that you have a conversation
with someone who oversees $6.6 trillion.
Yes, that's trillion with a T.
Samara Cohen is on the show today and she is a badass.
Samara is the Chief Investment Officer
of ETX and Index Investments at BlackRock.
That's basically all of BlackRock's iShares ETF funds,
all their index products,
which is quite a large domain, to say the least.
Samara has an affinity for the modernization of markets,
which is something that I think we share with her on Bankless.
Not only is she down in the BlackRock trenches,
not only is she down in the BlackRock trenches
building ETFs, talking to clients,
and producing market-based intelligence,
but she can also see things from a zoomed,
but she can also see things from a zoomed out view
and can discuss the long arc
of the interaction of technology and markets,
which I think is truly helpful
when we are currently in an age
in which blockchain tech is actually starting
to disrupt traditional markets.
This is one of my favorite conversations
I've had on Bankless in a long time.
In addition to all the other things
that I've already said about Samara,
she's also just so easy to talk to.
So I know you're going to enjoy this one at Bankless Nation,
so let's go ahead and get right into the conversation
with Samara Cohen from BlackRock.
Are you ready to swap smarter?
Uniswap apps are simple, secure, and seamless tools
that crypto users trust.
The Uniswap protocol has processed more than $2.5 trillion
in all-time swap volume,
proving it's the go-to liquidity hub for swaps,
with support for growing numbers of chains,
including Ethereum, Mainnet,
Base, Arbus and Polygon, ZK Sync.
Uniswap apps are built for a multi-chain world.
Uniswap seeks your transactions across its web interface,
mobile apps and Chrome browser extensions,
so you're never tied to one device.
And with self-custody for your funds and MED protection,
Uniswap keeps your crypto secure while you swap anywhere,
anytime.
Connect your wallet and swap smarter today
with the Uniswap web app or download the Uniswap wallet
available now in iOS, Android, and Chrome.
Uniswap, the simple, secure way to swap
in a multi-chain world.
The Arbitrum Portal is your one-stop hub
to entering the Ethereum ecosystem.
With over 800 apps, Arbitrum offers something for everyone.
Dive into the epicenter of DeFi,
where advanced trading, lending, and staking platforms
are redefining how we interact with money.
Explore Arbitrum's rapidly growing gaming hub
from immersed role-playing games, fast-paced fantasy MMOs,
to casual, luck-battle mobile games.
Move assets effortlessly between chains
and access the ecosystem with ease via Arbitrum's
expansive network of bridges and unrest.
Step into Arbitrum's flourishing NFT and creator space,
where artists, collectors, and social converge
and support your favorite streamers all on chain.
Find new and trending apps and learn
how to earn rewards across the Arbitrum ecosystem
with limited time campaigns from your favorite projects.
Empower your future with Arbitrum.
Visit portal.arbertrum.io to find out what's next
on your Web3 journey.
What if the future of Web3 gaming wasn't just a fantasy
but something you could explore today?
Ronin, the blockchain already trusted by millions
of players and creators is opening its doors
to a new era of innovation starting February 12th.
For players and investors, Ronin is a home
to a thriving ecosystem of games, NFTs, and live projects
like Axie and Pixels.
With its permissionless expansion,
the platform is about to unleash new opportunities
in gaming, DeFi, AI agents, and more.
Sign up for the Ronin wallet now to join 17 million others
exploring the ecosystem.
And for developers, Ronin needs your platform
to build grow and scale.
With fast transactions, low fees, and proven infrastructure,
it's optimized for creativity at scale.
Start building on the testnet today
and prepare to launch your ideas,
whether it's games, meme coins,
or an entirely new Web3 experience.
Ronin's millions of active users and wallets
means tapping into a thriving ecosystem
of three million monthly active addresses
ready to explore your creations.
Sign up for Ronin wallet at wallet.roninchain.com
and explore the possibilities.
Whether you're a player, investor, or builder,
the future of Web3 starts on Ronin.
Bankless Nation, I am very excited to introduce you
to Samara Cohen, the chief investment officer
of ETF and index investments.
Samara leads the team that manages 6.6 trillion,
6.6 trillion with AT of BlackRock's index funds
and I shares ETFs.
Samara, welcome to Bankless.
- Thank you so much for having me.
I'm glad to be here.
- So last time we spoke with BlackRock,
we spoke with Robbie Mitchnick,
who's the head of the digital assets team
at BlackRock in September of 2024.
It's now January of 2025,
and you are also not Robbie Mitchnick.
You are Samara Cohen.
Can you introduce yourself?
- Thank you, that was helpful.
- A little bit more for the audience
and illuminate a little bit of who you are
and what you do at BlackRock,
just so we know who we're talking to.
- Sure, I listened to the podcast with Robbie,
which was great,
and I am a listener of the podcast myself,
so very happy to be having the conversation
with you directly.
So I am, as you said, the chief investment officer
of ETFs and index at BlackRock.
I'm responsible for the portfolio management
of our index portfolios, our iShares ETFs,
and making sure they trade in the market
with the access, high quality
that investors expect from my shares.
I think of myself though,
just by way of background,
is really a career markets modernizer.
I've been in the ETF business for just 10 years now,
but when BlackRock first reached out to me at my,
the job I was at before then,
which was at a large investment bank,
I didn't know what an ETF was.
I had to Google, you know, what is an ETF,
which was actually relatively typical of a person
who was a growing up in the fixed income
and derivatives division of a bank then.
But my passion has always been making markets
more resilient and more transparent
and pretty much more useful for more people.
So that's what brought me from that job to BlackRock
and into the ETF business.
I work really closely with Robbie Mitch Nick,
who's our head of digital assets
and who has taught me a huge amount of what I know
about crypto and the digital assets world.
But really, ETFs are also,
and have been in markets a disruptive technology
that incite many of the same goals.
- What role does technology play in your job?
You called yourself a markets modernizer.
Maybe you could illuminate that modernizing word
a little bit more.
What does it mean and what have you done
to modernize markets?
Is this like an evolution of technology?
Is this new novel financial products?
How do markets become modernized
and how have you played a role in that?
- Sure, so I'll try not to get too nerdy
and weedy with this answer,
but I would argue that technology innovation
is foundational to the modernization of markets
and has been for literally millennia.
I like talking about this past spring.
I took my teen daughter to Paris
where she'd always wanted to go
and we went to the Louvre Museum
and the one thing I really wanted to see
'cause I knew it was there was this relic
from ancient Mesopotamia that was a,
it's considered a token actually, a clay token,
but it was how trade was conducted initially
thousands of years ago.
And it was a mechanism to exchange a,
what was then a real world asset
and kind of difficult to bring to the marketplace.
And that clay token thousands of years ago
was a technological breakthrough
that contributed to the next phase of markets.
So it was foundational then and it's foundational now.
Now, as we said ETFs and index are both in my title,
index strategies, which are the ability for an investor
with not that much money to commit
to actually diversify their portfolio
by buying hundreds or thousands of line items.
That wasn't possible actually until really
about 30 to 40 years ago.
And indexing as a portfolio strategy
actually came of age with the first commercial microchip
because it actually took more computing power
than had been available before
to take what had been really a mathematical concept
and turn it into a trading reality.
So that's like a few thousand years of history
with technology as the through point.
- Very interesting.
Yeah, I really, I think we at Bankless really appreciate
seeing the long arc of technology as it relates to markets.
So I think that's maybe something that we share.
So understanding the context of once we had clay tokens
representing real world assets
and going through the evolution of markets
to the world of ETFs as you've just illuminated,
we are now kind of entering this world of modern markets
integrating with blockchains
or blockchains integrating with modern markets by directional.
So now we've entered in the world
where there's now two very large ETFs.
And then I think this is just the beginning.
Maybe you could place us in history now in the modern era
where blockchain technology, blockchain assets
are now manifesting in the real world
and in traditional markets.
But then also it's like a foot in the door, right?
So where does this go for here?
Just place us in history as you see it, if you don't mind.
- Yeah, I love that question
'cause I think it is both a Bitcoin ETFs in the US
as a category and I should actually say
because our regulators want us to say they are ETPs,
not ETFs, exchange traded products
and definitions are important,
have been around like for exactly a year
almost to the day of this conversation.
And you're right, this has been, I think,
a watershed moment in markets
and yet also the very beginning.
So what's so important about the Bitcoin ETPs
in my view is that they really created a bridge
between these two worlds, between the crypto world
and the tradfi world.
One of the things that I think surprised us
to a degree this year was how useful that bridge was
to people on both sides.
We knew there were tradfi investors
that if they were going to allocate to Bitcoin,
wanted to do it in a familiar wrapper,
but there were a lot of digital native investors
who also found that the ETP wrapper served their needs
and we actually have some pretty good data
showing that there are investors
who bought their very first ETP in one of the Bitcoin ETPs
and are now buying other ETPs.
So hopefully it's helping both digital native
as well as tradfi investors
build more diversified portfolios
that are more customized to what they need.
So that's why it was such an important moment
and we really saw in all of the numbers
and the flows this year how embraced this bridge was.
But again, to your point, this is,
it's the story of one cryptocurrency
and it's a story, frankly, of tradfi rails
being very important to the bringing that cryptocurrency
more into the investor dialogue.
And so I think that's why it is still the very beginning
both as we see crypto rails
and the crypto financial ecosystem develop more.
And also hopefully in my view,
and I'm interested in hearing your view on this as well,
develop in an integrated way
with what already exists and works
because I think there's always a lot of passion out there
to completely disrupt and do things differently.
And sometimes that is the right direction
as a career markets modernizer.
I think we find a lot of times
that the best world is the one that creates bridges
and looks to best practices from multiple places.
- Yeah, I think people who are deeply crypto natives
and they believe in the cryptoization of everything
might resonate with something that I want to get your take on.
I think this got insepted into my brain with one
of the short stories from Andreas Antonopoulos.
He called it something like technology inversion
and he used the metaphor of dial-up internet
where the internet and data was squeezed through telephone lines
into people's homes and that's what dial-up internet was.
And now later, we actually just got broadband.
We just got cable internet and was much faster.
And now when you make a phone call with someone,
the phone actually goes on the internet
along with everything else that's on the internet.
The YouTube, Twitter, Facebook, Instagram,
and then also phones.
And so things flipped, things inverted.
And I think the correlation here,
the way to apply this to crypto
is that right now we have analog versions
of these crypto assets.
We have the Bitcoin ETF, the ETH or ETF,
but it's kind of the analog.
It's trying to squeeze the internet through dial-up
where I think crypto natives are really looking
for the inversion where all of a sudden more
of what BlackRock does, more of what the NASDAQ does,
is actually on a blockchain.
Maybe there is a BlackRock chain one day.
Maybe that's a little bit futuristic,
but I'm wondering your take on that perspective.
- So I agree with you.
That's the vision that crypto natives have.
I think for me, the question is,
is that the vision that serves markets
and investors best at this moment in time?
I'm not convinced that it is.
And a lot of times my lens and it's interesting.
I think my lens on crypto is kind of hard to extract
from my lens on being a parent.
My daughter is 16 and she was born October 10th of 2008.
And so she was born kind of 21 days
before the white paper was published.
And it was also during the great financial crisis.
And while these things are obviously not correlated,
that moment in time was a big one for me in my career
and determining kind of where I wanted to spend
the rest of my career and really wanting to,
if I was gonna continue a career in markets,
which is my passion and what I love doing,
I wanted to be a part of increasing resilience access
and transparency in markets.
I think though, that the vision of crypto,
which has huge benefits from a transparency
auditability perspective,
I think where I call into question
that crypto native vision is around the degree
of centralization that's ultimately most important.
'Cause again, as a parent,
the more decentralized a world,
the more you have to become the expert yourself.
And I think that really the reason trade intermediaries
have grown over decades, centuries, millennia
is because people wanna focus on the things
that their experts in and they are sometimes very willing
to trust and intermediary.
However, crypto can make that process of trust work better.
- I'd like to zoom into the here and now.
As you mentioned, the Bitcoin ETFs are almost one year old,
the Ether ETFs about six months old.
How should we evaluate the development and progress
and success of these ETFs?
How are they tracking versus expectations?
- So I think one of the,
I feel like I am becoming increasingly bilingual
in a trad five markets as well as crypto.
I'm much more like a,
now I'm more like a tourist crypto
and I have more fluency in trad five markets,
but it's interesting to me increasingly
to see the misperceptions on both sides of that divide.
And one of the misperceptions on the crypto side
is that the Ether ETFs weren't as successful
as the Bitcoin ETFs.
We're really by all accounts in the ETF world,
the Ether ETFs had really successful launches.
So how do we measure that?
First and foremost, for us in the industry,
a successful ETF is one that delivers
what it's supposed to deliver.
So it tracks the underlying index with absolute precision.
It's one of the reasons that Bitcoin ETFs became important
because what we were hearing from investors
was that they didn't have many ways outside
of actually holding Bitcoin in self custody or on exchange.
They didn't have many ways to hold it
in a kind of trad fi wrapper
where they could view it alongside the rest
of their portfolio in a way that tracked.
They were buying a future ZTF,
which as you probably know,
for reasons where imposition limits mistrack,
they were buying proxy stocks.
And so the tracking of the ETF,
the precision of that is number one, how we measure success.
Number two is market quality.
And what we mean by that is it takes really an ecosystem
of players to create trading volumes,
liquidity, access on exchange.
For us, it was the authorized participants
who were agreeing to do create and redeem in the ETF.
So making sure all of those things are in place,
we call that market quality.
Both the Bitcoin ETF and the E3TF have tracked,
they've had high market quality, high participation.
Now the flows have been different.
And this kind of gets me to, you know,
misperception number two.
And there's definitely misperceptions on both sides,
but that's that creating an ETF drives flows.
It doesn't.
Investors and investor sentiment drives flows.
And in 2024, for investors,
the thesis around Bitcoin was much more tangible
than the investment thesis around ETH.
And that explains the, you know, disparity in flow.
However, they've both been,
I think that, you know, the Bitcoin ETF,
as you probably know, really beat all ETF records in history.
But the ETH was still in the top 20% of ETF launches
in the United States this year.
So we feel that both is successful.
- And it's interesting to hear that you're saying that
it's really the marketing, the narrative,
the identity of the ETH ETF that can be the reason
why investors buy versus don't buy.
And I think this is definitely something we learned
as an industry is like the Bitcoin story.
It's just so easy to tell.
It's very simple, 21 million limit, it's digital gold.
That's it.
And then the Ether story just doesn't have that same firepower,
that same punch.
We asked Robbie, I remember a similar question to this,
but that was again back in September.
And also since then, Ether ETF flows has picked up significantly
in the last month or so.
I'm wondering if there's any new conversations
that you're hearing from clients or any,
just what's the gossip mill sound like
in the terms of people who are buying the Bitcoin ETF
or the Ether ETF?
Is there anything different than when we checked in
four or five months ago?
- I don't think there's that much that's different.
I will give my take on a couple of things that you just said.
And actually, David, as a fun fact,
I should tell you how I started listening to the podcast
'cause I think I'd listen to it from time to time.
And if you recall, the SEC really surprised the industry
with its approval of ETH ETFs that happened in May.
We were, the industry was ready for it to happen
and we were kind of had the playbook
from the Bitcoin ETPs, but that was a surprise.
And so, and if you remember,
and you guys covered this very closely,
that period of June through early July,
we really weren't sure when trading would start.
And so we were looking at everything art portfolio,
readiness, trading, operational,
as well as the education strategy
around how we would position the ETFs when they came out.
So I was one weekend, a lot of my favorite content
in crypto has actually been through podcasts
versus a lot of the stuff that I normally read.
And so I was just searching through podcasts
and I saw this podcast called "The Great ETH Pitch Off"
and I thought, well, this sounds like it could be useful.
And so I listened to that.
And I actually thought it was really,
I thought, I mean, you guys were funny,
but also very thoughtful and educational.
And so that was actually when I--
- That's what we go for.
- Yeah. (laughs)
Well, you get the combination of things.
You've covered a lot of things really well, I think,
but that's when I started listening to the podcast.
So, but I will say this,
I think your frustration then,
which is a little bit of what you just said,
was that it was just harder to explain.
It was a tougher narrative.
I actually think that's true,
but I don't think that's the crux of the issue.
Investors are smart and the,
what we call self-directed or individual investors
who are really driving the success right now
of the Bitcoin ETP range from really small investors
to very sophisticated investors.
It's a very broad space.
And I think, generally speaking,
they understand the difference.
They don't buy the investment thesis
at this moment in time to the same degree.
It's not as relevant as the Bitcoin thesis is
in a moment of time where we have
heightened geopolitical tension,
concern over kind of broad-based disruptions,
concern over the dollar, deficits.
So, all of these things play really well
into the Bitcoin thesis,
on top of which what's really an investor psyche right now,
I think, is that 2022 was a brutally hard year
for trad-fi investors,
because stocks and bonds went down together.
That was a historical event,
and it really made people think about
how do I diversify my portfolio?
What are the, is there,
are there alts that can create some sort of ballast
in a traditional kind of 60/40 equity bond portfolio?
And there's a really interesting analysis you can do
around the potential that Bitcoin plays in that scenario,
where at the same time, particularly for the US investor,
who is in whether it is through an active strategy
or an index strategy,
likely pretty exposed to mega-cap tech,
I think often they feel that the ETH story
is less of a diversifier and more of an amplifier
to some of the exposures they have.
So, I think that both the industry,
as well as investors are on that educational journey,
and it's not that they don't get it.
I think that Bitcoin has just been more relevant
at the portfolio conversation right now.
- Yeah, yeah, there's always just maybe,
narrative, market fit, asset, market fit
for the times that we are inside of.
And I think there is just a lot of geopolitical relevancy
over the last few years,
and maybe Bitcoin is simply just a stronger player
in that sort of environment.
I'm wondering, does BlackRock provide any recommendations
in terms of allocation for investors interested
in holding exposure to Bitcoin, the Bitcoin ETP
or the Ether ETP?
Is that something that you guys do?
And if so, what are those recommendations?
- So, we're not an investment advisor.
We don't provide investment advice,
but we do put out investment research
and it's generally rooted in risk
and how we look at portfolio risk.
And we do that across asset classes, countries, strategies.
And we have started writing about Bitcoin.
We haven't yet written about ETH in the portfolio context,
because most of this year,
I mean, again, ETH is six months old versus Bitcoin,
a year old.
So, initially with Bitcoin,
it was really educating around Bitcoin, the asset class,
and also importantly,
for the digital native investors who understand Bitcoin,
educating around ETPs and the ETP wrapper.
And we're still on that journey with ETH.
Over the last few months, though, we did write twice,
and we'll continue to do so on Bitcoin and the portfolio.
So, we wrote about Bitcoin as a diversifier,
and the reasons we think it's interesting
or relevant for investors
who are thinking about an allocation to Bitcoin
to think about the potential diversification aspects
of Bitcoin versus equities and bonds
and in the traditional 60/40 portfolio.
Then we actually took it a step further.
And I think probably about a month ago,
we wrote a piece that I think is really interesting
on portfolio interactions of Bitcoin.
And that's the first place we talked about
potentially sizing an allocation.
And this, of course, is for an investor who has determined,
I am interested in participating in Bitcoin
because there's lots of investors,
particularly on the institutional side who aren't there yet,
but for investors who want to incorporate Bitcoin
in their portfolios,
how do you think about it in the context
of a diversified portfolio?
And we thought an interesting framing
given that so many investors are already in some way
exposed to the Mag7 stocks.
We looked at portfolio risk contribution
of different levels of Bitcoin allocation
and how that would compare to a Mag7 stock.
And that's not to say that Bitcoin is at all
like any of those stocks is different,
but taking a risk-centered approach
to how to think about a Bitcoin allocation
and its contribution to overall portfolio risk,
we thought was something that investors
would really understand.
And that came out of a lot of the conversations
that we have with our clients.
And where we came out in that piece
was that a 1% to 2% allocation to Bitcoin
got you to the same level of risk contribution
as a Mag7 stock and going above 2%
would exponentially increase the risk contribution.
So if you were to go above 2%,
you were really making a very strong view
on Bitcoin specifically versus trying to keep it
in the bounds of this diversified portfolio.
- Now, who are the people that are consuming this information?
Who is, I'm sure, very robust analysis?
Who's the intended audience
for who is supposed to hear that information?
- So we talked to investors across the spectrum.
Largely the investors that we talk to directly
are advisors who have their own clients
and we also talk to institutions.
And then we do make a lot of information available
on our website for individual investors.
We'd have to check though, David, before,
I'm not sure if this piece is, I forget,
like if it's on the website for anybody,
but we do put, the diversifier piece is out on our website
for everybody, the portfolio allocation,
maybe for advisors and institutions,
but we really write for all of those audiences.
- Yeah, I guess since you have $6.6 trillion
in ETFs and index products,
the, maybe the answer to who is reading this is some chunk
of whoever is operating that $6.6 trillion of ETFs
and index products.
- Well, but remember this, the $6.6 trillion
doesn't have any crypto in at all.
That's all of our equity ETFs are fixed income ETFs.
The only crypto that we hold because you would know this,
one of the things about the index in ETF portfolios
is they are completely transparent.
We publish holdings on a daily basis.
So the only crypto in those portfolios right now
is actually in the two crypto ETFs, Bitcoin and ETH.
- Right.
I would like to get your opinion on what we want to see
out of the ETFs in 2025.
If there was like a rubric of sorts with things
that you wanted to see the Bitcoin ETP
and the ETH ETP check off as achievements in 2025
of this year, what might be on that list?
What's some things that you feel like are pretty safe
that we're gonna get?
What are some things that are maybe a little bit harder
that you're optimistic for?
And then maybe what are some potential stretch goals?
- Well, so first of all, I think that this work being done
around Bitcoin and the portfolio construct is really important.
And I hope we see more of that in 2025.
I hope that conversation becomes less about Bitcoin
or not Bitcoin and more about how is Bitcoin manifesting
in the portfolio?
Where's it useful?
Where's it not useful?
And look, the experience of the next few months
and the next year is gonna be very instructive
in terms of where that goes.
It's important to remember that relative to lots
of other asset classes, Bitcoin still has
a pretty limited history.
There's lots of investors who say, hey, conceptually,
this makes sense, but it's really hard for me to do the type
of backtesting and analytics that I'd want to do
with kind of call it 10 meaningful years of trading data.
So the more market cycles we weather,
the more data that comes available, the easier it is
to kind of integrate Bitcoin into the broader conversation
around risk and asset returns.
So that's number one.
Number two, which is a little bit more specific,
is I think the launch of options on the Bitcoin ETPs
was a really important moment in November.
Generally speaking, options ecosystems
are really good for markets.
They tend to create more balanced trading dynamics.
You will have buyers on the way down, sellers on the way up.
And so seeing how that plays out
is going to be really important.
On the other hand,
and I was having this conversation with someone yesterday
actually with Bob Pezani on CNBC,
innovation and complexity go hand in hand.
And there are lots of people who are really excited
about launching and pitching options-based strategies.
And some of those will be really useful for investors.
And some of them may be really hard to understand.
And so I think the more options are incorporated
into product strategies around Bitcoin,
the more important it is that we really put out
good, clear education on what investors are buying.
But generally speaking,
options help investors go in multiple directions.
It helps them kind of tailor their exposures,
participate with limited downside, achieve income.
And so I think the development and the use of options ecosystems
is going to be interesting.
We've even seen interesting dynamics in the last few weeks
where as you expect when options were launched,
there was so much more demand for calls versus puts.
So upside protection versus downside protection.
That started flipping a little bit.
And that's going to give us a lot of information
and transparency around investor sentiment.
And that level of transparency actually
is really a creative to healthy markets.
So when I think about the hallmarks
of a more mature, resilient market,
the development of this options ecosystem in ETPs,
I think will be helpful both for the underlying crypto assets
and also probably for their digital native derivative markets
which don't have as much transparency as they will need
to really achieve more uptake among investors.
- Now I'm going to quote a friend of the podcast,
Alex Thorne here, "BlackRock Eyebit Options
are absolutely dominating.
The volume on Eyebit is dominating
versus the vanilla ETFs.
Also, ETH A, the BlackRock Ether ETP
has also recently started to take the lead
on volume on the Ethereum side.
And the question is, what has BlackRock done
to foster that growth?
Or was that all just emergent
and just part of the product of maybe the elections
or just the times that we are in?
Is there anything from the top downside of things
that BlackRock did to help promote volumes
on the options in the Ether A product?
- Well, remember, we're not options market makers,
we're not option traders, but we do invest a lot of time
and attention in the options ecosystem
because again, going back to how do we measure
a successful ETF, high levels of market quality
and in our experience, ETPs that have developed
options ecosystems around them
have higher market quality than those that don't.
So we think investing in options ecosystems
is an important use of time and resources.
We spent a lot of time with NASDAQ on it, of course,
and Eyebit options actually ended up launching
the day before the rest of the suites, I think,
because we are just very focused on options
and making them available.
Well, when we think there's investor demand for them
and there clearly was in this case,
but what's interesting is we also,
what's differentiating about the iShares platform
is that, I mean, you gave some of the headline numbers,
but that's actually not the most exciting part of it.
I think what's exciting about the platform
is that we cover virtually all asset classes,
all countries, and so we have very deep ties
into the trading ecosystem and are able to work
very closely across the trading ecosystem
to understand what do market makers need
in order to commit their own capital and technology
to making markets and participating.
And there's a lot of things around Bitcoin
that are very attractive to market makers.
It's a high volatility asset.
The volatility of volatility is high.
And it also has this, like what we think of as positive
skewingness, the volatility, historically, generally,
has gone up when prices go up, right?
Which also makes it attractive.
So we spend a lot of time on those dynamics
and we engage a lot in the options ecosystem.
With over $1.5 billion in TVL, the MEAath protocol
is home to ME, the fourth largest
ETH liquid staking token, offering one of the highest APRs
among the top 10 LSTs.
And now, CMEAath takes things even further.
This restaked version captures multiple yields
across Kerak, Eigenlayer, Symbiotic, and many more,
making CME the most efficient
and most composable LRT solution on the market.
Metamorphosis, season one, dropped $7.7 million
in cook rewards to MEAath holders.
Season two is currently ongoing, allowing users
to earn staking, restaking, and ABS yields,
plus rewards in cook MEAath protocols,
governance token, and more.
Don't miss out on the opportunity to stake,
restake, and shape the future of MEAath protocol
with cook.
Participate today at meath.mantle.xyz.
Solo is transitioning from a mobile first,
EVM compatible layer one blockchain
to a high performance Ethereum layer two,
built on OP stack with EigenDA and one block finality,
all happening soon with a hard fork.
With over 600 million total transactions,
12 million weekly transactions, and 750,000 daily active users,
Solo's meteoric rise would place it
among one of the top layer twos,
built for the real world and optimized
for fast, low cost, global payments.
As the home of the stablecoins, Solo hosts 13 native
stablecoins across seven different currencies,
including native USDT on opera mini pay,
and with over four million users in Africa alone.
In November, stablecoin volumes hit $6.8 billion,
made for seamless on-chain FX trading.
Plus, users can pay gas with ERC 20 tokens like USDT and USDC,
and send crypto to phone numbers in seconds.
But why should you care about Solo's transition to a layer two?
Layer two's unify Ethereum, L1's fragmented.
By becoming a layer two, Solo leads the way
for other EVM compatible layer ones to follow.
Follow Solo on X and witness the great solo havening,
where Solo cuts its inflation in half
as it enters its layer two era
and continuing its environmental leadership.
- And you talked about how options in volume
just really make for a very high quality product,
a high quality market.
I would imagine that the existence of options also
is just legitimizing for Bitcoin.
It's something that fits into
the traditional finance mental model
for what finance looks like.
What is that unlocking?
Is that unlocking further institutions
to deploy more capital?
Is it, what does the legitimacy and the market quality
unlock for the Bitcoin ETFs and the Ether ETFs
as they achieve them?
- I think I'd replace the word legitimacy
with transparency and access.
So options provide a new level of transparency and access.
And I would say it's been interesting to me
on my own crypto journey because theoretically,
there is so much transparency in crypto.
But actually, if you are a trader or an investor,
there are so many different sources
of price information, transparency is harder to procure
in crypto markets in some ways than you would expect it to.
And so bringing volatility instruments
onto exchanges and listed exchanges
so investors can kind of standardize
and source and commit capital to prices,
which allows us to really see where volatility is
and where it's trading.
That level of transparency and access
is a game changer for markets
and wasn't there to the extent I might've thought it would be
a few years ago in crypto.
So I think that's kind of point number one.
And point number two is absolutely we often see
that investors who want exposure to an asset class,
but for whatever set of reasons
aren't ready to commit fully to the underlying,
they will come to the asset class via the options market.
We've actually seen that historically,
I told you there's a lot of parallels
between exchange traded funds and options.
Exchange traded funds have grown explosively
over the past 20 years.
And a lot of institutional investors
came to exchange traded funds initially
through options on exchange traded funds.
They thought they appreciated the idea of the exposure,
but they wanted to have more of a limited capital
outlay and limited downside to start, and they came to the
underlying wrapper via the options market.
So that's an important dimension too.
- There's a famous quip in Bitcoin land
that the price of Bitcoin is its marketing department.
Price is the best marketing for Bitcoin.
And I'm wondering if you just have any anecdotes,
you can share about what it was like
since the Bitcoin ETFs were launched
when Bitcoin crossed $100,000, a historic milestone.
What was that like on the inside of BlackRock?
Was there any communications with clients or fund advisors
or anything like that?
Any anecdote you can share that's related to the idea
that price is the best marketing for Bitcoin?
- I think education is the best marketing for Bitcoin.
I think education and work around risk
and had a harness risk in a diversifying way
and look at portfolio interactions.
From my perspective and how we talk to investors,
that's actually the best marketing for Bitcoin.
Actually, I think it's important that investors
are reminded despite the highs that Bitcoin
was reaching into the end of the year,
that this, although price volatility in Bitcoin
has dropped meaningfully in the last few years,
it still is by any measure, a risky volatile asset
versus pretty much anything else
that investors have in their portfolios.
And that's actually part of what creates relevance
for it right now.
If it didn't have those volatility characteristics,
it might not have the same investment thesis
as a diversifier that it has,
but actually keeping in front of investors
in particularly long-term investors,
which is largely who we are talking to,
those facts has actually been a lot more significant
than the price action of Bitcoin.
And actually, this gets me back to this point
around misperceptions.
I do think in the crypto world,
there was this view that success in the ETF
was that the price of the underlying went higher
and that is absolutely not how we would ever measure success
of an ETP.
It's does it effectively provide access, have market quality
and play a role in an investor's portfolio.
I was wondering, there's potentially in the Ethereum land,
there's future upgrades to the Ethereum blockchain
that may or may not impact the fundamentals of Ether
or just the blockchain at large,
but then that's also true for Bitcoin as well.
Does BlackRock have any view about future upgrades
to the protocols of which it has ETFs for?
Would BlackRock ever take a stance
on upgrade proposals out of these blockchain systems?
- So first, I would say BlackRock is about 20,000 people.
So BlackRock is never gonna have a kind of monolithic view.
The best person to talk to about that,
of course, would be Robby Mynchnick
and Robby will certainly have views.
Certainly have views.
And I think with respect to how we engage in the industry,
there are many times that we do go out
and speak to our views.
Although generally speaking,
if I look at other trading environments, trading ecosystems,
our views will be kind of rooted in the principles
of what makes an ecosystem the most useful
for us and our clients versus,
'cause we generally favor just open architecture
and interoperability, which at its core,
operating at our scale is something we need
everywhere we transact.
Generally speaking, having to operate
in a closed ecosystem can be very limiting for us.
It's one of the reasons from a tokenization perspective,
one of the pivots we did make pretty publicly
over the last couple of years
was leaning much more towards public
versus permissioned blockchains.
So I think in terms of stances you'll hear from us,
it would be more along those lines
versus one kind of crypto platform versus another.
But scalability and the aspects of scalability
and particularly the prerequisites
for our counter-parties to participate
is something I would expect us to be vocal about.
- One thing that I think the entire crypto industry
is hopeful for is that we are not at all
close to being done with the increased ETFization,
the indexization of some of our crypto assets.
We have our number one and number two, Bitcoin and Ether,
but I think we're hopeful by the end of hopefully 2025,
we at least have signs of number three
and number four and maybe number five.
And then hopefully in five to 10 years,
there's more than we can really count.
Does BlackRock have any other plans
for other digital asset ETFs?
Or what would it look like to start to see some plans
starting to come together?
- So I guess I actually have a question for you
if you wanna share your thoughts on this,
but it's why do you think that is so important
and of such focus if, you know,
'cause I sometimes again worry
that going back to misperception number one,
that you launch an ETF and the price of something goes up,
that's a misperception.
And I wonder whether some of that misperception
is driving the excitement
over kind of multiple coin ETFs.
We route our decisions based in like investment thesis
in the portfolio, but what do you think is driving that?
- Oh, I think it is absolutely exactly what you identified.
I think if you are a large community member
of a respective blockchain ecosystem
and it does not yet have an ETF,
you see the ETF as a catalyst
for price appreciation of your respective crypto asset.
And to be fair, that is what happened with Bitcoin.
Maybe it's not exactly what happened with Ether.
Maybe Ether didn't really exactly
have a very strong price appreciation
post the launch of the ETFs, but Bitcoin certainly did.
And that is what the narrative has become
in the world of crypto.
And the narrative I think is because the ETFs unlock
access to investors in a particular asset
that did not exist prior.
There's also some amount of legitimization.
So if something has gotten an ETF,
it's legitimized by tradfi.
It's opened up to potentially pools of capital
that it didn't have prior.
And also there is a regulatory de-risking as well
where maybe this is less relevant
for the incoming administration,
but for the previous administration,
an ETF is kind of considered as a shield of armor
against Gary Gensler and the SEC.
And so I think some combination of those reasons,
everyone in the crypto industry wants an ETF
for the respective asset that they hold.
- Yeah, interesting.
I think that there's a lot to unpack there.
Categorically launching an ETF does not magically create
price appreciation, and by the way,
this is a conversation I have had for the past 10 years.
Wherever I go in the world,
I might be in a country that has a relatively
less developed stock market
and the CEO of the exchange there will come and say to me,
"Hey, can you guys come and launch ETFs here?"
Because the idea that they have is you launch ETFs
and magically it creates liquidity and demand
for the underlying and it really works in the reverse way.
So I think what's important is really to parse out
what will the investment thesis be
for each of these native tokens
of these different blockchains?
How do you measure it?
How do you describe cash flows to it?
And how do you look at risk?
What's unique about Bitcoin is not that it is the oldest,
oldest is funny, it's a year old,
but oldest US listed ETP,
it's that it actually has a very unique investment thesis
where the kind of future price is entirely a function
of the level of adoption given the scarcity,
finite supply and Bitcoin.
And this is the part, yes, it's easier to understand
because Bitcoin is generally only trying to be one thing,
this borderless store of value.
However, despite the more complex investment theses
of these other tokens,
you still need a way to ascribe cash flows
and to look at them one to the other.
And that's the story that has to be told.
And from my perspective,
I think most successful ETP launches will follow that.
But to your point, there's lots of excitement
and I think the regulatory path may become much clearer
to launch an ETP on any token that you want.
But without speaking for other issuers,
the way we approach it is really like reading the work
and what we hear from our clients has a role
in their portfolio right now.
- Me and Ryan, we do the weekly roll up every Friday
and we look at the inflows into the Bitcoin ETFs
and inflows into the E3 techs.
- I know you do.
- Yeah, right, yeah.
I mean, BlackRock's usually like the number one
their inflow on a weekly basis.
And just looking at it right now,
Bitcoin has 35, almost $36 billion of net inflows
into the Bitcoin ETFs.
And I think when people in the crypto industry hear that,
they are thinking, well, that is $36 billion
of buying pressure.
Now, granted, there could have been maybe
a majority percentage of that inflows
that was sold by actual physical Bitcoins
sold by crypto investors and then rebot
in the ETF package just for whatever reason,
tax advantages, convenience advantages.
And so maybe only a minority of that inflow pressure
is actually true net buying.
But nonetheless, people think that some percentage
of this inflows into the Bitcoin ETFs
is true buying pressure that did impact the price
of Bitcoin in a positive direction.
Is that wrong?
Is that naive?
How should we think about this?
- I don't think it's wrong.
I just think that there's Bitcoin buying in all wrappers.
And you see that in the ETP flows.
Now, one of the things that we really like to look at,
we call it the secondary primary ratio,
is that imbalance of demand and those net inflows,
like when people actually, because of course,
a market maker doesn't have to create new shares
of the ETF and it's when they create new shares
of the ETF, they deliver coin to the ETF
and you actually see the inflows.
There is nine times as much trading
that is actually happening between buyers and sellers
of the ETP such that no coin gets exchanged at all.
That's a really interesting statistic.
I think in terms of looking at market sentiment
is how much like incremental exchange
is happening outside of actual inflows.
But yes, categorically inflows show an imbalance
of buying versus selling.
And some of that is net new buying,
but there's net buying happening across other wrappers as well.
I don't think it's a function of the existence of the ETP yet.
I think that there are institutions
that may do their first sizable Bitcoin allocations
via the ETP wrapper where they haven't had any allocation so far.
That has not largely been the story though of 2024
and that gets back to, this was a big year,
but it really is the beginning,
that conversation around institutional adoption
and also a wealth advisor adoption,
that's gonna be the important story of 25 and beyond.
- Beautiful, I do actually wanna get back
to the original question of does BlackRock have any plans
for other digital asset ETPs
and what can you share with us on that front?
- I mean, we're pretty public about it
and I do get a lot of commentary on crypto Twitter,
which we should talk about for a second
'cause I think crypto Twitter can be unproductively mean.
But our-- - Oh, I'm aware.
- Yeah, our plans right now are around Bitcoin and ETH.
That's where we hear from our clients.
There is the portfolio level interest
with respect to where our focus is right now.
We have focuses obviously in digital assets beyond the ETP.
We're very focused on tokenization
and tokenization of treasury funds.
We're very interested in kind of the future path
around stablecoins and our,
when we think about our digital asset strategy,
it's kind of those pillars of crypto stablecoins
and tokenization.
So for us, there is a world beyond new coins in an ETP,
but with respect to our near-term strategy,
our focus is really Bitcoin and ETH.
- Understood, understood.
I wanna get into a little subject about regulation,
but maybe first before we get there,
we are about to have a new administration,
one that has positioned itself to be more free markets,
more pro-markets, Gary Gensler,
will be resigning in six days.
Maybe that's more relevant to us crypto natives
and it is to BlackRock,
but we are very excited about it
on the crypto side of things.
Has this incoming new administration changed any strategy
or impacted anything at all
as it relates to BlackRock's involvement
in the crypto industry?
- Yeah, look, I think first of all,
nobody's in place yet to your point.
We are a few days away from inauguration
and to be super clear,
the SEC impacts absolutely everybody in financial markets,
certainly in the US and I would argue as well around the world.
So we care deeply and we engage very closely with the SEC.
I think taking a pretty big step back
from kind of the current administration,
US markets have generally done a better job
at supporting innovation and supporting investors
at the same time than anywhere else in the world
and that's why US markets kind of have the prominence
that they do today.
It is that combination of support for innovation
and appropriate investor protections
that I think are really the hallmark
of what we do really well.
So I'm pretty excited and optimistic
that that is the direction we will return to.
There's been less transparency
and that's played out pretty publicly,
certainly around the crypto ETPs,
but in other ways as well.
Now recall a lot of what impacted this SEC
has nothing to do with crypto.
It really goes back to some of the stock market dislocate,
when I say, sorry, this SEC,
some of the stock market volatility and dislocations
that characterized 2020, 2021,
like one of the big themes in global markets right now
is this heightened participation by individual investors.
So like you or me trading through an online brokerage account
and there was a huge spike in that in the US
at the beginning of 2020
because a lot of trading platforms
started offering commission-free trading.
People were at home over COVID
and getting more comfortable with technology
and then a lot of people got stimulus checks
and so those three things combined
created a lot of like individual traders in the markets
and importantly, a lot of those traders actually kind of stayed
in the markets and became index and ETP investors,
but markets have changed and are changing in the US
and around the world because of the participation of retail
and that has just created a wave of regulatory focus
that has really dominated the last few years.
But I think to your point, yes,
I think that it is exciting to be looking ahead
to a more innovation supportive environment,
but I will say I really hope
and I think that you and Ryan have done a really nice job
of covering in a balanced way,
the impact just positive and negative of regulation,
a lack of regulation, a lack of guardrails
can really undermine investor confidence
and maintaining and growing investor confidence
is one of the single most important things
for this market to meet its potentials.
So my hope and my engagement
and I hope yours as well is gonna really be around
how do you strike the balance between those two things?
- So anything that BlackRock is anticipating for
for regulation in 2025,
there's a potential set of bills out there,
a stablecoin bill, anything that BlackRock is hopeful for
or anticipating in 2025?
- Yeah, so we're hopeful that a lot of the basics
get established so things like definitions,
things like jurisdiction,
like who's the regulator, who's responsible?
There's a lot of work that has to be done
to simply figure out like who's gonna engage,
who can you ask questions to, who do you work with?
Because to get this right is really going
to require collaboration by the public and private sector,
which is why I think it's generally a positive sign
that there's a number of private sector experts
that are signaling the fact that they are going to be
engaged in positions of influence.
That's going to be really important.
That's always important in terms of areas
of new technologies.
So number one, the basics, like jurisdiction,
who's responsible, definitions, you know, what's a security?
And in terms of the existing bills, whether it's fit 21,
which I think is, you know, an important step forward
that probably could be a little better integrated
with some of, you know, what exists in TradFi.
I think what happened in the last couple of years
is what you see in some of the bills
is a footprint of a lot of crypto engagement.
And in some cases, the development
of a separate crypto ecosystem,
which I'm not sure in the long term,
that's the best outcome because you want existing players
to be able to invest and not face
a whole duplicative set of regulations.
So ideally, you have, you know, something that works
for people that are new and something that works
for people that, like, aren't new,
but want to participate in this space.
But I think fit 21 goes in that direction,
as does the stablecoin bill.
And I think outside of those bills, my hope.
And I think my expectation as well
is that there will be more work around interoperability
so that more TradFi market experts
can play a bigger role in the future.
- Now, specifically about the way that BlackRock
is built, there are two teams at BlackRock
that I know of that touch digital assets,
the digital assets team and then also the ETFs team,
which you've run.
How do these two teams engage with each other?
What does it look like when these two teams
are talking with each other?
- I actually think it's cooler than that.
So we have a digital assets team
and I think one of the most important things we did
as a firm in terms of progressing our digital assets strategy
was putting in place the team, you know,
with Robbie's leadership.
But what Robbie did is he really made digital assets
the work of everybody at the firm.
So years ago, I mean, we were spending hours together,
Robbie, you know, to his credit as an incredibly patient,
resilient and thoughtful person,
but he spent a lot of time educating the businesses
and giving all businesses.
So ETFs, index, trading, cash, securities lending, derivatives,
giving all the businesses the opportunity
to consider what are your use cases,
you know, helping us, bringing and, you know,
kind of being a digital asset consultant
so that every business could consider
what the applications were to them.
And what we found in our business, you know,
when I started working with him years ago was
we had this initial excitement
and this was very typical in TradFi Lego Bitcoin.
Let's put that to the side.
It's like this blockchain technology
that's really gonna be the game changer.
We came up with all of these use cases.
We piloted some things.
Nine times out of 10, we realized, okay,
we need a better technology solution,
but blockchain isn't necessarily the answer,
but that was actually the impetus
for some of our bigger technology upgrades
was doing that work, where we knew there was a friction
and we had to fix it, but then eventually, you know,
both of those things really became clear
where there were more industrialized use cases.
But I guess that's a long winded answer to your question.
These aren't teams that sit in distinct verticals.
We have a digital assets team
that kind of cuts across as a horizontal
that lets us really consider in a much broader way
what our potential use cases and opportunities are.
- So I guess it's really just a matter of Robby
innovating with all the other parts of BlackRock
and really convincing them that crypto
for that particular part of the organization
is the right tool for the job
if and when the moment comes like crypto is truly
the right tool for the job.
Is that a way to interpret things?
- I think that's right.
And it also means, you know, you have to have somebody
who has skin in the game and is accountable
for their actual business results to commit
and then to partner with the digital assets team.
And that's worked pretty well.
- Well, Robby, we're rooting for you.
Samara, I think I can also speak for Ryan,
who's not here at the moment, obviously,
that we are both very honored that you listened
to the podcast on such a frequent basis.
Who would you like to hear as a guest on the podcast?
Who would really nerd snipe you
as a very fascinating guest that you'd like to hear from?
- Well, I'm incredibly interested in some
of the new policy voices that come out,
particularly over the next couple of months.
I think I told you one of my favorite episodes
was when you had Austin Campbell on,
I actually reached out to him after the podcast
and just met up with him and talked to him.
He, like me, has a derivatives-tradified background,
so I knew we had a lot in common.
And he wants to create a better financial system.
And so I think people like that who,
oh, I have another misperception for you, David.
Sometimes when you do these episodes,
like the ETH pitch off for Austin Campbell,
you guys preface it with, okay, bankless citizen,
this episode is not for you.
It is for your, like, grandparents
who we're trying to educate around this.
And I would say, like, we're not all that old.
There've been a few times, I'm like, really?
Really, like, I'm not your, like, parent maybe,
but like, grandparents, that's a little bit of a stretch.
I actually think that there are a lot of people
in positions like mine who care deeply
about the, like, the legacy they're leaving in markets.
And again, I'm a parent of two teen kids.
There's nothing that's more important to me
than what their financial futures are gonna be
and how they engage with the financial system
and how we create resilience and access
and transparency for them.
So I do think that my hope for you,
I know you guys get super excited
when you talk about, like, blocks and blobs
and, you know, this, this, like--
- I do like the blobs.
- I know you like the blobs.
And I know it's a thing that scales eth,
but, like, that's kind of the extent for me.
But I think thinking about how you can talk to that,
that broader audience with people like the Austin Campbells
of the world is, would be really impactful.
- Yeah, Austin Campbell was a great guest
as you have also been a great guest.
And sometimes it's actually really the guest
that really helps us get the message out.
And I think that's something that we've done here today
on the podcast.
One last question for you, Smart, before I let you go,
just open-ended, what are you excited about?
What are you excited about for 2025?
What are you looking forward to either professionally
or personally in the world of markets?
I know you really like markets.
So what kind of, like, keeps you going?
What gets you excited for 2025?
- This is gonna sound corny, but I'm gonna go with it.
- What gets me excited is hope and optimism.
And I have a lot of that right now.
I think that 24/23 was a tough year.
I think you and I saw each other at the,
the, yeah, at Permissionless
where you actually, like, had a fight with someone, right?
- Yeah, I found a guy, yeah.
- Yeah, okay.
So, like, you guys have, like,
there is some branding there, but I get it.
- And I guess I will say it.
- To be clear, it was a karate combat
orchestrated fight between two consenting adults
who agreed to do this inside of a professional environment,
not just a random fight.
- Fair enough, well, like, I get that.
But a lot of the promotional material was like,
I felt like around this fight.
And I just bring that up because there was a lot of
anger at the system, like, more than I had expected.
And that was very, there were a couple of things
that were eye-opening for me at that conference.
That was one of them.
Crypto, additional assets.
- Anger at the system.
What do you mean by that?
- I think anger at the state of the regulatory environment.
Like, anger at the idea that it was just like,
it was a moving target to know what you could do
and couldn't do and how do you invest your capital?
And I think that's, you know, that's a bad environment
for innovation and for growth.
But the degree of just kind of the atmospherics around it
was a bit diverting from the mission and the goals.
So my hope is now we can really focus
on the mission and the goals,
which is, I believe, to create a more transparent
and accessible financial system for,
and obviously crypto is way beyond finance.
I just live in the financial realm of it.
So that's really my hope for 2025.
And I think that we are on our way towards doing that.
- Well, I hope that there are some things
that are lining up in the crypto industry
and outside of the crypto industry
that really can foster that.
Some people are calling for a golden age
in crypto innovation.
We finally have very abundant, very cheap block space.
Developing has never been easier.
And now, regularly wise, we have pretty clear skies.
And so hopefully we can put that optimism and to some use
and kind of get back to exactly what we were saying,
which is mission driven to espouse
what is so good about blockchain and crypto
and bring this industry into its golden era.
So Tamara, thank you so much for joining me
on the Bankless Podcast today.
We really am very honored to have had you.
- Thanks a lot for having me.
This was fun.
- Bankless Nation, you guys know the deal.
Crypto is risky.
You can lose what you put in,
but we are headed west.
This is the frontier.
It's not for everyone,
but we're glad you are with us on the Bankless journey.
Thanks a lot.
(upbeat music)